Zhiwei Chang

Data/Research Scientist

Curious and persistent researcher with over 10 years of experience in theoretical and numerical (bio)physics ready to transfer to new role as Data Scientist. I love to enter new territories, acquire new knowledge and skills to solve the most challenging problems ahead. Being sceptic and imaginative both — with a can-do-it-all, grit and teamwork mentality — I am equipped to make unique contributions to the team.

SKILLS

Programming & Software

Python, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Jupyter Notebook, Scikitlearn, SQL, MATLAB/Octave, Mathematica, Git, Linux shell, Office, LTFX

Technical

Regression (Linear, Multiple-Linear, Logistic, Polynomial, SVR, Random Forest), Classification (K-NN, SVM, Random Forest, Native Bayes), Clustering (K-means, Hierarchical), Deep learning, Project Management, Data Cleaning & Interpretation, Scientific writing & documentation

EXPERIENCE

202I.7 - CURRENT

I am interested in solving real-life problems which could benefit general audiences. Currently I am working on a hobby project which is to analyze and predict the housing prices in Lund, Sweden, a city I am living. As a fun project, I am also rewritting Andrew Ng's machine learning course exercises Matlab code in Python and implement corresponding algorithms in Scikitlearn as a comparison. I also explore and analyze the data sets in Kaggle. In addition, I solve algorithms and data structure problems in AlgoExpert. These projects can be found in my Github.

2018.5 - 2021.6

Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Postdoc Fellow/Independent Researcher

This position is mainly focused on measuring protein structures using solidstate nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR). During the COVID when MIT was closed, I developed a new physical theory to analyze/design the electromagnetic pulses used to manipulate protein nuclear spins. This independent work resulted two manuscripts which are now ready for submission. I also took the famous machine learning course by Andrew Ng on Coursera during this period.

2011.9 - 2017.7

Lund University

Ph. D Researcher

I switched to a more interdisciplinary area - biophysics, to do my PhD. Using protein and water proton as a probe, working closely with my supervisor, I derived quantum mechanical theories related to NMR and wrote corresponding simulation packages to study protein dynamics. This work resulted in 5 first-authorship papers in a well-known peer-reviewed journal.

2008.9 - 2011.7

Northwest Normal University

Master Student

As my thesis project, I was tasked with calculating the atomic structure of the "superheavy" element 117 and its lighter homologue Astatine. With very little supervision, I published 5 theoretical and simulation papers and some of my predictions have been cited and confirmed by CERN.



Dag Hammarskjölds väg 5H, 22464, Lund, SE

(+46) 765943720

zhiweichang10@gmail.com https://zwchang.github.io

www.linkedin.com/in/zhiwei-chang-015b2355

EDUCATION

Postdoctoral Researcher 2018.5 - 2021.7

Biophysical Chemistry

Massachusetts Institute of Technology, USA

Doctor of Philosophy 2011.9 - 2017.7

> Biophysical Chemistry Lund University, Sweden

Master of Science 2008.9 - 2011.7

Theoretical Physics

Northwest Normal University, China

Bachelor of Science 2003.9 - 2007.7

Theoretical Physics

Beijing Normal University, China

SCHOLARSHIPS & AWARDS

3-year International Postdoc Grant 2018 (3.15 million SEK, Approval Rate: 15%)

Swedish Research Council (Vetenskapsrådet)

Hakon Hanssons Travel Grant (15000 SEK) 2013

Lund University

Full Ph.D. Scholarship 2011

Lund University

"Outstanding Paper" Award 2010

Northwest Normal University

LANGUAGES

MOTHER TONGUE Chinese

English FLUENT Swedish ELEMENTARY

TEACHING

Two semesters as a teaching assistant tutoring Thermodynamics and Electromagnetism; three semesters as a lab instructor tutoring several Thermodynamics experiments.

PUBLICATIONS

Twelve manuscripts: two submitted, ten published (peer-reviewed), ten first-author, including J. Chem. Phys., J. Phys. Chem. A, etc. Some key publications can be found in my Google scholar (zwchang@mit.edu).

 \subseteq